today we're going to talk about layouts layouts
is a really powerful tool where you can select
all your fixtures individually if you want to you
can build the layout view exactly as you want it
it's completely customizable you can change
colors you can change fixtures you can change
the appearances you can add groups you can add
all kinds of different things so in this tutorial
we're going to build what you see on the screen
right now it's very simple it doesn't take very
long so keep watching and i'll show you how it
works we are starting right here where we left off
the last time when we built all our presets using
all the swiping commands you know this view and
if you haven't seen that episode you can go back
and watch episode 5 it's about presets and using
the swipey commands right now we need to close
this window down or clear this window and open
another one to our layout view before we start
we need to clear the screen and if you remember
how to do that we go up to the little icon up
here we press it and we say delete this screen
now the screen is black we need to find the layout
view the layout view consists of two different
things the layout view itself and some selection
tools next to it so if we start with opening the
layout view here you go in under common and you
press the layout view this opens up the layout
in a full window we need to scale it a little bit
down because we need the room for something else
over here in the side we can make it maybe
make it a little bit bigger we press the
square up here and we go into pools and we
find the layouts over here we need the layout
pool over here because we can filter down what's
in the layout view but first of all we need to to
build the rest right down here we need to save our
group so open our group window we do that under
the pools command and we find the groups and they
can see this is the groups we stored the last time
we can scale it down all the way down because
we only need these four right next to the
group we need our sequences open so we open the
pools and we go down and we find the sequences
i just stored a few ones here so we can see the
layout view in action so this is basically the
view we need we can extend this further we can
use it with macros we can do all kinds of stuff
i just wanted to explain to you the simplest
way to do a layout view so we store this view
we can go up here into the command section
we can press store and we can store the
view over here so right now we have stored
our view we'll just call it layout lay out
there we go right now we see nothing if you worked
on the GrandMA 2 you know that you would choose
your fixtures and you would store and merge them
into your layout view you would actually store it
into these groups over here on the GrandMA
3 this has changed you up just a little bit
now you assign your fixtures into your layout view
so what we can do first is choose all our vipers
we do it like this we say alt plus a which is our
assign key if you have your shortcuts turned on
now we have all our vipers we say assign and we
just push the screen up here that assigns all the
fixtures all the mac vipers into our layout view
we can zoom in just a little bit and we can go
into the setup menu over here in the setup menu
you have the option of moving things around you
can add stuff you can delete stuff let's just try
to do that so let's just clear out of this one
and we say the arrow up here and we say
number one we need to move it we take this one
this is the move command we can just move it
wherever we want it and we just move it up here
it's snapping is on right now if snapping
is not on you go into this command in here
and you can see all the different options you
have in here snap to grid it's much easier to
work with i think it's much easier to work
with but whatever makes you happy you can do
whatever so you basically just move them around
until they are positioned the way you like it
now all our vipers are lined up the way we want
it let's do the same with our auras i'm just
going to speed this one up just a little bit
so you don't have to wait for me finishing it
we stored all our vipers we stored all our auras
let's do the same for the atomics but let's just
do it in a different way we assign the atomics
like we usually do then we place it here in
the center between number six and number seven
there's 12 in total and then we do like we did
in the 3d view we align them we take the the dash
right here and we turn the dial and then we can
position it like this this as well so basically
you can do whatever you can do it with your
fingers or with your mouse manually or you can do
it with the align key that's all up to you let's
take our dimmers as the last thing and when
we have positioned them we can start working
on storing some groups in the window as well
let's store some groups into the view as well
and as you remember before we set all our vipers
and then we set assign like this now we're going
to do a little bit different we're going to say
assign all our vipers and you can say assign group
1 and we can simply just push a button up here
and it assigns all our vipers this is the group
containing all our fixtures so if we go out of the
setup menu and we push this one it selects all our
vipers because it's the same group as you have
down here you simply move the reference up here
so into setup again maybe we should
just clear out here and say okay this
is a little small we need it to be a little
bit bigger you have the width and the height
right here so you can basically just say 100 in
the width or maybe that's too big maybe it's a
and then the height is 75 as
well then we have another square
but it's a little bit bigger than than the
fixtures themselves let's do the same for the uh
for the mac auras we assign this one up here we can
do the same with the atomics we assign it up here
and all our dimmers we assign them right here
let's do the same for the width and the height
let's set them to 75 in width and 75 in height to
make them the same kind of same size of the other
groups so right now we have we need to space that
maybe a little bit down so we get some more space
that's the beauty another beauty of the layout
view you can set it up exactly the way you want it
if you need more space if you need to cram
everything together because you are working on a
large rig it's all up to you so now we're almost
here let's just make sure they are all straight
there we go there we go so right now we have all
our vipers all our auras all our atomics and all
our dimmers and if we push them out of setup menu
push them you can see it selects all the fixtures
which is brilliant now you can basically build any
group you want you can in your dimmers you can say
okay you can build a group for the first two or
the next three or whatever on your vipers you
could do an art group an even group for the left
fixtures the right fixtures that's all up to you
and whatever makes your world easier whatever
makes your programming easier you should do
lastly let's make some different colors for these
groups over here let's go back into the setup menu
let's clear out of the selection let's choose
all our vipers with right clicking you go into
the menu like this you have the appearance tab
right here we need to select something different
and we have the options of choosing some different
colors i think i'll choose the red one for all the
vipers and you see it instantly changes to red
now it's much easier to distinguish them from
each other let's do the same for the auras we
picked the blue color let's do the same for the
atomics we can pick the green color and
let's do the same for the dimmers we can
choose the cyan color so now we built an
easy layout view it didn't take long even
with explanation so without any talking you can do
this in three or four or five minutes you should
do this every time you come out with a new rig
because it makes it a lot easier to work with
afterwards right now all this is stored into
our default view up here but we need to copy
this a few times if you need to separate it in
different views say we want a view where we only
have all our vipers for instance i mean this is
not really important on a small rig like this but
if you're working on larger shows you definitely
need this so if you take the default up here
and you simply swipe down and you say copy and
you put it down here now we copied it down here
still the default we can say we can rename
it with using our swipes we can say vipers
and we can simply go in here
select all of these ones
say delete and then select all these ones and
they're gone we have the default view up here
with all of it and we can select here with only
our vipers let's do that again we copy this one
like this and we place it down
here oops we rename it to aura
there we go and we simply delete all the
vipers and all the atomics and all the dimmers
and so on and so forth this is how it works
so we have the default view with all of it
we have the vipers we have the auras let's
copy the default view down here oops
wrong button let's copy this one
down here and call it atomics
and let's do the same up here let's copy this
one down here and we can call this dimmer
there we go let's go to the atomics and we
can delete all our vipers auras and dimmers
like this and we can go into dimmer and we
can delete basically everything else but the
dimmers this gives you an advantage when you are
working the larger shows you can simply select
i know i need to work with my vipers just clear
everything else out and now it's only the vipers
up on the screen you can still change this i mean
you all have the default view now you have it in
the center and it fills out almost the entire
screen which is fine you can go into the vipers
and say okay now i have a little bit more room
maybe i need to position it differently or maybe
i need to make these bigger so you can do this
and say okay now there's a room for them to be
100 high and 100 wide like this if you want to
this gives you a little bit more detail you can
move it around like you want to it's all up to
you how you how you want it but this is basically
the layout view how it works it's really really
simple to work with and it's a it's a great great
great tool for for working on on larger shows
the last thing i wanted to show you was simply
that the layout view gives you some feedback when
you work with it if you go out of setup menu and
you choose all your vipers and you say at full you
see they instantly change to a open white and if
you go into my first view here and you choose
magenta or magenta and you go back you can see
they also change color into magenta so having the
layout view open when you program actually helps
you a lot because you can always see the level of
the light you can always see the color you can see
if there's an effect running or something like
that so it's really really really powerful so i
hope you enjoyed this video i hope you'll give a
like and i definitely hope to see you next time on
this channel so thank you very much for watching
all the way to the end i'll see you next time bye